<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Teachings on Mario Jurić :: Research</title>
    <link>http://research.majuric.org/teaching/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Teachings on Mario Jurić :: Research</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2016 Mario Jurić</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/teaching/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>ASTR 497: Big Data in Astronomy: Hands-on with Large Surveys</title>
      <link>http://research.majuric.org/teaching/astr497/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://research.majuric.org/teaching/astr497/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;location&#34;&gt;Location&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When: 11:00a-12:20p, Mon &amp;amp; Fri, Spring quarter 2014-2015&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where: PAB B356A (Physics-Astronomy Building, 3rd Floor)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;details&#34;&gt;Details&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enrollment: 10 max&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Credits: 3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prerequisites: ASTR 300 (or ASTR 599)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;description&#34;&gt;Description&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The next decade of astronomy is shaping up to be defined by large surveys and datasets. After JWST, the next two U.S. flagship projects, both in space -- WFIRST -- and on the ground -- the LSST -- are survey telescopes. Already today, major astronomical surveys are routinely collecting hundreds of terabytes of images, creating databases with billions of objects and several billion measurements. This changes how we approach and analyze such datasets -- large surveys astronomers are becoming data scientists.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The goal of this course is to introduce you to research with large survey data, teach you how to think about such data sets, and provide an overview of what is or soon will be available. We will:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn about how large observational data sets are changing astronomy
&lt;li&gt;Introduce modern tools and techniques for working with large data sets (incl. databases, data access, analysis, and visualization)
&lt;li&gt;Introduce and work hands-on with existing data sets (including SDSS, WISE, Kepler and others)
&lt;li&gt;Learn about major upcoming surveys (including PanSTARRS, Gaia, and LSST)
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will be a small, very hands-on course, with significant emphasis on learning-by-doing rather than classical lecturing. Our language of choice will be Python (and related data science libraries). It is complementary to ASTR 480 (note: ASTR 480 is NOT a prerequisite).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ASTR 597: Big Data in Astronomy: Introduction to Large Surveys</title>
      <link>http://research.majuric.org/teaching/astr597/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://research.majuric.org/teaching/astr597/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;location&#34;&gt;Location&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When: 3:30-5:00, Mon &amp;amp; Tue, Winter quarter 2014-2015&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where: PAB B356A (Physics-Astronomy Building, 3rd Floor)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;description&#34;&gt;Description&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
While surveys have been with us since the dawn of science, the precision, depth, and the several orders of magnitude larger datasets of today are unprecedented. Today, major astronomical surveys are routinely collecting hundreds of terabytes of images, creating databases with billions of objects and several billion measurements. This shifts the focus from data collection to data mining, from examination of small samples to studies of entire populations, from identification by eye to automated algorithmic search. Large surveys astronomers are becoming data scientists.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of this course is to prepare you for research with large survey data, teach you how to think about such data sets, and give you an overview of what is or soon will be available. We will:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn about how large observational data sets are changing astronomy
&lt;li&gt;Introduce tools and techniques for working with large data sets (incl. access, analysis, and visualization)
&lt;li&gt;Introduce and work hands-on with existing data sets (including SDSS, WISE, Kepler and others)
&lt;li&gt;Learn about major upcoming surveys (including PanSTARRS, Gaia, and LSST)
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While focused on astronomical surveys, the course may be suitable advanced undergraduates and non-majors interested in learning about working with large scientific data sets.
&lt;/o&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;details&#34;&gt;Details&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Syllabus, course materials, etc: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mjuric/ast597b&#34;&gt;https://github.com/mjuric/ast597b&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;UW Canvas course Entry: &lt;a href=&#34;https://canvas.uw.edu/courses/972091&#34;&gt;https://canvas.uw.edu/courses/972091&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
