<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mario Jurić :: Research on Mario Jurić :: Research</title>
    <link>http://research.majuric.org/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Mario Jurić :: Research on Mario Jurić :: Research</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2016 Mario Jurić</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>ASTR 497: Big Data in Astronomy: Hands-on with Large Surveys</title>
      <link>http://research.majuric.org/teaching/astr497/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://research.majuric.org/teaching/astr497/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;location&#34;&gt;Location&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When: 11:00a-12:20p, Mon &amp;amp; Fri, Spring quarter 2014-2015&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where: PAB B356A (Physics-Astronomy Building, 3rd Floor)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;details&#34;&gt;Details&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enrollment: 10 max&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Credits: 3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prerequisites: ASTR 300 (or ASTR 599)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;description&#34;&gt;Description&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The next decade of astronomy is shaping up to be defined by large surveys and datasets. After JWST, the next two U.S. flagship projects, both in space -- WFIRST -- and on the ground -- the LSST -- are survey telescopes. Already today, major astronomical surveys are routinely collecting hundreds of terabytes of images, creating databases with billions of objects and several billion measurements. This changes how we approach and analyze such datasets -- large surveys astronomers are becoming data scientists.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The goal of this course is to introduce you to research with large survey data, teach you how to think about such data sets, and provide an overview of what is or soon will be available. We will:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn about how large observational data sets are changing astronomy
&lt;li&gt;Introduce modern tools and techniques for working with large data sets (incl. databases, data access, analysis, and visualization)
&lt;li&gt;Introduce and work hands-on with existing data sets (including SDSS, WISE, Kepler and others)
&lt;li&gt;Learn about major upcoming surveys (including PanSTARRS, Gaia, and LSST)
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will be a small, very hands-on course, with significant emphasis on learning-by-doing rather than classical lecturing. Our language of choice will be Python (and related data science libraries). It is complementary to ASTR 480 (note: ASTR 480 is NOT a prerequisite).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ASTR 597: Big Data in Astronomy: Introduction to Large Surveys</title>
      <link>http://research.majuric.org/teaching/astr597/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://research.majuric.org/teaching/astr597/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;location&#34;&gt;Location&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When: 3:30-5:00, Mon &amp;amp; Tue, Winter quarter 2014-2015&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where: PAB B356A (Physics-Astronomy Building, 3rd Floor)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;description&#34;&gt;Description&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
While surveys have been with us since the dawn of science, the precision, depth, and the several orders of magnitude larger datasets of today are unprecedented. Today, major astronomical surveys are routinely collecting hundreds of terabytes of images, creating databases with billions of objects and several billion measurements. This shifts the focus from data collection to data mining, from examination of small samples to studies of entire populations, from identification by eye to automated algorithmic search. Large surveys astronomers are becoming data scientists.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of this course is to prepare you for research with large survey data, teach you how to think about such data sets, and give you an overview of what is or soon will be available. We will:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn about how large observational data sets are changing astronomy
&lt;li&gt;Introduce tools and techniques for working with large data sets (incl. access, analysis, and visualization)
&lt;li&gt;Introduce and work hands-on with existing data sets (including SDSS, WISE, Kepler and others)
&lt;li&gt;Learn about major upcoming surveys (including PanSTARRS, Gaia, and LSST)
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While focused on astronomical surveys, the course may be suitable advanced undergraduates and non-majors interested in learning about working with large scientific data sets.
&lt;/o&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;details&#34;&gt;Details&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Syllabus, course materials, etc: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mjuric/ast597b&#34;&gt;https://github.com/mjuric/ast597b&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;UW Canvas course Entry: &lt;a href=&#34;https://canvas.uw.edu/courses/972091&#34;&gt;https://canvas.uw.edu/courses/972091&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Galactic Structure</title>
      <link>http://research.majuric.org/project/galactic-structure/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://research.majuric.org/project/galactic-structure/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m interested in the structure and evolution of our galaxy, the Milky Way. This research has resulted in discoveries of streams in the Galactic halo, &lt;a title=&#34;Milky Way Models&#34; href=&#34;http://research.majuric.org/wp/?page_id=68&#34;&gt;accurate models of Milky Way&amp;rsquo;s stellar content&lt;/a&gt; that form the basis for predictions related to LSST science, as well as a fast GPU-accelerated stellar catalog code &lt;a title=&#34;galfast&#34; href=&#34;http://research.majuric.org/wp/?page_id=28&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;galfast&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;is-the-milky-way-s-stellar-halo-triaxial&#34;&gt;Is the Milky Way&amp;rsquo;s stellar halo triaxial?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My most recent Milky Way-related research explored the triaxiallity of the stellar (and dark matter) halo of the Galaxy. My collaborators and I have approached this problem in two different ways – by using the imaging of Sloan Digital Sky Survey III (SDSS III) for a nearby but wide-area (D &amp;lt; 20kpc) halo study, and by using the Canada-France-Hawaii Telescope Legacy Survey&amp;rsquo;s (CFHT-LS) “wide”&amp;rsquo; (W) survey for a pencil beam look into the deep (15 &amp;lt; D &amp;lt; 35 kpc) halo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the SDSS III study my student, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.astro.yale.edu/people/ana-bonaca&#34;&gt;Ana Bonaca&lt;/a&gt;, showed that:
&lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The halo in the northern Galactic hemisphere exhibits a clear asymmetry that can be attributed to the Virgo Overdensity&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The VOD is significantly larger than previously measured, covering &amp;gt;= 2000 deg2 of the sky&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;By comparing with SDSS III southern Galactic hemisphere catalogs, we showed that the VOD cannot be due to a tilt in the stellar halo ellipsoid and conclude it&amp;rsquo;s likely of external origin and,&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Accounting for VOD and the Sagittarius stream, we detected no sign of triaxiallity of the Milky Way stellar halo to D ~ 20kpc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a title=&#34;An Update on the Nature of Virgo Overdensity&#34; href=&#34;http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2012AJ....143..105B&#34;&gt;Bonaca, Juric, et al., 2012, AJ&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-dual-halo-of-the-milky-way&#34;&gt;The Dual Halo of the Milky Way&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the CFHT-LS study, lead by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.astro.caltech.edu/~bsesar/&#34;&gt;Branimir Sesar&lt;/a&gt; (Caltech), we have attempted to detect triaxiallity or signs of significant clumpyness in the intermediate (15 &amp;lt; D &amp;lt; 35kpc) halo. Using the CFHT-LS data photometrically recalibrated we showed that the Juric et al. (2008) halo model describes the observations to D &amp;lt; 25kpc remarkably well. However, beyond that range the halo shows a steepening (to n ~ -4.5). We interpret this as the likely transition from a halo component created ``in-situ&amp;rdquo;, to an accreted component that dominates the outer halo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a title=&#34;The Shape and Profile of the Milky Way Halo as Seen by the Canada-France-Hawaii Telescope Legacy Survey&#34; href=&#34;http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2011ApJ...731....4S&#34;&gt;Sesar, Juric and Ivezic, 2011, ApJ&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;mapping-the-structure-of-the-milky-way-using-the-sdss&#34;&gt;Mapping the Structure of the Milky Way using the SDSS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an ongoing series of papers led by Zeljko Ivezic and entitled “The Milky Way Tomography with SDSS”:
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Tomography I: Stellar Number Density Distribution&#34; href=&#34;http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2008ApJ...673..864J&#34;&gt;I. Stellar Number Density Distribution (Juric et al. 2008)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2008ApJ...684..287I&#34;&gt;II. Stellar Metallicity (Ivezic et al., 2008)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Tomography III: Kinematics&#34; href=&#34;http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2010ApJ...716....1B&#34;&gt;III. Stellar Kinematics (Bond et al. 2010)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Tomography IV.: Dissecting Dust&#34; href=&#34;http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2012ApJ...757..166B&#34;&gt;IV. Dissecting Dust (Berry et al. 2012)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;V. Luminosity Function (Juric et al. in prep)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
my collaborators and I constructed one of the most accurate empirical models of Milky Way stellar number density, metallicity, and kinematics, and demonstrated the feasibility of directly mapping the Milky Way using the wide- area, multi-band, photometric data set such as the Sloan Digital Sky Survey (SDSS).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the photometric parallax method, Juric et al. (2008) estimated the distances to ~48M main-sequence stars observed by the SDSS, mapped their three-dimensional number density distribution, and produced three- dimensional maps of Galactic stellar number density at heliocentric distances from 100 pc to 20 kpc. These maps are a departure from the traditional methods of forward-modeling of star counts, in which counts in color-magnitude space are fitted to models that rely on a number of poorly constrained functions: the mass function, mass-luminosity relation, and density laws of the postulated components (e.g. exponentials and power laws). Instead, using the density maps the Milky Way&amp;rsquo;s structure can now be studied with few a priori assumptions about its components. Indeed, with our data the need for each component, and its properties, is determined a-posteriori from the data rather than a priori from a set of input assumptions. Such maps can also be more directly compared to simulations, which predict structure and substructure significantly more complex than the simple analytic models traditionally used to describe the Milky Way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mapping the Milky Way is one of the key science drivers for LSST.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Large Survey Database</title>
      <link>http://research.majuric.org/project/lsd/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://research.majuric.org/project/lsd/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;large-survey-database&#34;&gt;Large Survey Database&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://research.majuric.org/img/lsd-ps1-footprint.jpg&#34; style=&#34;float: left; width: 400px; margin: 20px; margin-left: 0px;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://lsddb.org&#34;&gt;Large Survey Database&lt;/a&gt; (LSD) is a Python framework and DBMS for distributed storage, cross-matching and querying of large survey catalogs (&amp;gt;10&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt; rows, &amp;gt;1 TB). The primary driver behind its development is the analysis of &lt;a href=&#34;http://pan-starrs.ifa.hawaii.edu/public/&#34;&gt;Pan-STARRS PS1&lt;/a&gt; data. It is optimized for fast queries and parallel sweeps of positionally and temporally indexed datasets. It transparently scales to more than &amp;gt;10&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; nodes, and can be made to function in &amp;ldquo;shared nothing&amp;rdquo; architectures. It&amp;rsquo;s been written and maintained by &lt;a title=&#34;Mario Juric&#34; href=&#34;http://research.majuric.org/wp/?page_id=37&#34;&gt;Mario Juric&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An LSD database consists of a set of vertically and horizontally partitioned tables, physically stored as compressed HDF5 files. Vertically, the tables are partitioned into sets of related columns (&amp;lsquo;column groups&amp;rsquo;), grouping together logically related data (e.g., astrometry, photometry). Horizontally, the tables are partitioned into partially overlapping ``cells&amp;rdquo; by position in space (lon, lat) and time (t). This organization allows for fast lookups based on spatial and temporal coordinates, as well as data and task distribution. The design was inspired by the success of Google BigTable (&lt;a href=&#34;http://research.google.com/archive/bigtable.html&#34;&gt;Chang et al., 2006&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our programming model is a pipelined extension of MapReduce (&lt;a href=&#34;http://research.google.com/archive/mapreduce.html&#34;&gt;Dean and Ghemawat, 2004&lt;/a&gt;). An SQL-like query language is used to access data. For complex tasks, MapReduce ``kernels&amp;rdquo; that operate on query results on a per-cell basis can be written, with the framework taking care of their distribution, scheduling, and execution. The combination leverages the users&amp;rsquo; familiarity with SQL, while offering a fully distributed computing environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LSD adds little overhead compared to direct Python file I/O. In tests, we sweeped through 1.1 Grows of PanSTARRS+SDSS data (220GB) less than 15 minutes on an 8-core machine. In a cluster environment, data rates of 14Gbits/sec (I/O limited) were achieved. Based on current experience, we believe LSD will scale to be useful for analysis and storage of LSST-scale datasets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LSD has and active user community, and has been successfully applied to storage and analysis of a multitude of large astronomical data sets, including PanSTARRS PS1, SDSS, PHAT, WISE, PTF, 2MASS, GALEX, and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-information&#34;&gt;More Information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Website:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a title=&#34;Large Survey Database website&#34; href=&#34;http://lsddb.org&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lsddb.org&#34;&gt;http://lsddb.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mailing list archive:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a title=&#34;Mailing list archive&#34; href=&#34;http://goo.gl/l5EFil&#34;&gt;lsd-users google group&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source code:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mjuric/lsd&#34;&gt;https://github.com/mjuric/lsd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grant:&lt;/strong&gt; STSci/HST-HF-51255.01-A (&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Mapping Galactic Structure, Formation, and Evolution with Pan-STARRS&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;, Hubble Fellowship)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Large Synoptic Survey Telescope</title>
      <link>http://research.majuric.org/project/lsst/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://research.majuric.org/project/lsst/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lsst-data-management-project-science&#34;&gt;LSST Data Management Project Science&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am the Project Scientist responsible for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://dm.lsst.org&#34;&gt;Data Management
System&lt;/a&gt; for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://lsst.org&#34;&gt;Large Synoptic Survey Telecope&lt;/a&gt;.
The LSST Project Science group&amp;rsquo;s task is to ensure LSST&amp;rsquo;s DM system delivers
excellent science quality data products and services (we&amp;rsquo;re the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mountaingoatsoftware.com/agile/scrum/product-owner&#34;&gt;Product
Owners&lt;/a&gt; of
the LSST&amp;rsquo;s Data Management system).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LSST&amp;rsquo;s team of 80+ researchers and IT experts,
distributed among LSST in Tucson, Princeton University, University of
Washington, SLAC, NCSA and IPAC, is developing the data processing system
for LSST.  The work includes the science pipelines (the image processing software to
detect and characterize sources on images, detect moving objects, build
co-added images, difference images, etc.), the middleware layer that manages
the robust execution on large computing clusters, the distributed database
(call qserv) to store and serve the resulting catalogs, as well as
the user interfaces enabling the access to and analyses of data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the size and expected quality of the dataset, we&amp;rsquo;re breaking new grounds in virtually all these areas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Image processing:&lt;/strong&gt; We&amp;rsquo;re developing a new (general purpose) O/IR image processing system and researching algorithms capable of controlling measurement systematics to the level required for characterization of Dark Energy. We&amp;rsquo;re pushing the state-of-the art in identification and linking of Solar System objects, to make LSST the most efficient asteroid-finding mission in history.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Middleware:&lt;/strong&gt; Our science pipelines must scale from operating on a single laptop with a hard drive, to a 100,000+ core cluster with a mass store system (tape library), and live through 8+ years of construction and 10+ years of operations. The transient alert system must reliably difference images and detect transients in 60 seconds.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Infrastructure:&lt;/strong&gt; 6.4 GB images will be transmitted within seconds over 10+ gigabit networks from Chile to NCSA in Illinois. LSST is one of the drivers of multi-gigabit long-haul network infrastructure build-up between Chile and North America.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Database:&lt;/strong&gt; Our database must store 10+ PB of LSST catalogs, and enable complex analyses and data mining. We are developing a fault-tolerant distributed database product, based on existing well-developed open-source tools, to meet this need.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;User interfaces:&lt;/strong&gt; We are developing UIs designed to enable querying and visualization of the LSST data set, as well as enable machine-driven access to it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information can be found at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://lsst.org&#34;&gt;LSST Project&lt;/a&gt; web page, and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://dm.lsst.org&#34;&gt;LSST Data Management&lt;/a&gt; pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;group-members&#34;&gt;Group Members&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mario Juric&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Melissa Graham&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Colin Slater&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eric Bellm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jim Bosch (Princeton)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;David Ciardi (CalTech/IPAC)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-information&#34;&gt;More Information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grant:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nsf.gov/awardsearch/showAward?AWD_ID=1227061&#34;&gt;NSF/AST-1227061&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>galfast</title>
      <link>http://research.majuric.org/project/galfast/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://research.majuric.org/project/galfast/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;i&gt;galfast&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2008ApJ...673..864J&#34;&gt;Juric et al. 2008&lt;/a&gt;, see also &lt;a href=&#34;http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2010AAS...21540125J&#34;&gt;Juric et al. 2010, 401.25, BAAS, 42&lt;/a&gt;) is a GPU-accelerated generator of flux-limited realizations of Galactic models. It is capable of generating catalogs for arbitrary, user-supplied Milky Way models, including empirically derived ones. The built-in model set is based on fits to SDSS stellar observations over 8000 deg&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; of the sky, described in the &lt;a title=&#34;The SDSS Milky Way Model&#34; href=&#34;http://research.majuric.org/wp/galactic-structure/milky-way-models/&#34;&gt;“Milky Way Tomography with SDSS”&lt;/a&gt; series of papers (Juric et al. 2008, Ivezic et al. 2008, Bond et al. 2010). It includes a three-dimensional dust distribution map based on Amores and Lepine (2005), and Schlegel et al. (1998).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the capability to use empirically derived models, &lt;i&gt;galfast&lt;/i&gt; typically produces closer matches to the actual observed counts and color-magnitude diagrams. In particular, &lt;i&gt;galfast&lt;/i&gt;-generated catalogs are used to derive the stellar component of  “Universe Model” catalogs used by the &lt;a title=&#34;LSST: Processing and Analyzing Petascale Datasets&#34; href=&#34;http://research.majuric.org/wp/survey-science/lsst/&#34;&gt;LSST Project&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A key distinguishing characteristic of &lt;i&gt;galfast&lt;/i&gt; is its speed. &lt;i&gt;Galfast&lt;/i&gt; uses the GPU (with kernels written in NVIDIA C/C++ for CUDA) to offload compute intensive model sampling computations to the GPU. On a mid-range GPU (single Tesla S1070 GPU), it is typically 25x to 200x faster than similar CPU implementations, depending on the details of the simulation being performed. This enables generation of realistic catalogs to full LSST depth in hours (instead of days or weeks), making it possible to study proposed science cases with high precision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, using the acceleration techniques developed for &lt;i&gt;galfast&lt;/i&gt;, observational error distributions derived from observations or simulations (e.g., ImSim, in case of LSST), and the storage/query engines from &lt;a title=&#34;Large Survey Database&#34; href=&#34;http://research.majuric.org/wp/survey-science/large-survey-database/&#34;&gt;LSD&lt;/a&gt;, we should be able to fully forward-model large survey datasets. Besides understanding the global properties of the observed datasets, this will allow us to mine for and discover rare and unexpected features.&lt;i&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-information&#34;&gt;More Information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Documentation: &lt;a title=&#34;galfast Documentation&#34; href=&#34;http://mwscience.net/trac/wiki/galfast&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://mwscience.net/trac/wiki/galfast&#34;&gt;http://mwscience.net/trac/wiki/galfast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Source on github: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mjuric/galfast&#34;&gt;https://github.com/mjuric/galfast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
